<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<Fichier>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891216-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-16-89 0016EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama Bjt   12-16 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama, Bjt,0601</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Blasts Appointment of Noriega as Chief Executive</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to restore AP logo</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The opposition says Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega's appointment as chief executive is just another
effort to perpetuate his dictatorship and makes democracy an even
more distant dream for Panama.
   The general's hand-picked legislature declared Panama in a state
of war on Friday and named Noriega chief executive to combat what
it called U.S. aggression.
   ``To confront this aggression, the job of chief of government of
Panama is hereby created, and Manuel Antonio Noriega is designated
to carry out these responsibilities as maximum leader for national
liberation,'' the resolution said.
   Noriega, chief of the Panamanian Defense Forces and already the
power behind the government, is wanted in the United States on
federal drug trafficking and money laundering charges.
   Washington has tried to oust him from power for 2{ years with
diplomatic pressure and economic sanctions. But the general has
weathered the U.S. pressure as well as military coups attempts in
March 1988 and in October.
   The 510-member assembly's resolution says Noriega can appoint
public officials, control foreign relations, convene the assembly
and ``make decisions on whatever other matter or unforeseen
circumstance'' affects the nation's interests.
   ``The Republic of Panama is declared to be in a state of war
while the (U.S.) aggression lasts,'' said the resolution, passed by
acclamation by the People's Assembly.
   Noriega was sworn in on the spot.
   ``This designation is a new imposition of a dictatorship that
exists only to perpetuate Noriega's power,'' a statement from the
Democratic Alliance of the Civic Opposition said.
   The alliance said Noriega's new title is a ``mere symbol.''
   Noriega, it said, ``has been exercising unlimited power since
the day he took command of the Defense Forces in 1983'' and the
appointment shows ``the dictatorial nature'' of his regime.
   It said Noriega's appointment was ``a step backward in the
search for a democratic solution'' that would only ``serve to
produce more and more complex problems'' for Panama.
   Nonetheless, the opposition reaffirmed its determinaton to
``keep struggling to achieve liberty and justice for the Panamanian
people.''
   In Washington, U.S. Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence
Eagleburger on Friday called Noriega's appointment ``a charade and
nonsense.''
   ``As far as we are concerned, at least, there is no government
in Panama anyway,'' he said.
   As head of the government, Noriega holds the same title as the
late dictator Gen. Omar Torrijos, his mentor.
   Noriega claims the U.S. indictments are part of a plot to renege
on the 1977 treaties signed by President Jimmy Carter and Torrijos
that turn over operation of the canal to Panama at the end of the
century.
   Noriega has propped up a succession of powerless presidents
while he controlled the country.
   Panama has not had an elected government since Sept. 1, when the
last presidential and legislative terms ended.
   Elections were held May 7 to fill those spots, but Noriega
annulled the balloting before all the votes were counted.
International observers said the opposition was winning by a 3-1
margin.
   Noriega then named Francisco Rodriguez, a friend since high
school, provisional president and appointed the nation's mayors and
county chairmen to the People's Assembly. Rodriguez's position was
expected to become a largely ceremonial post.
   Assembly members were applauded for attacks on the United
States. One asked the government for guns for all citizens
``because what we have to do here is kill gringos and pro-gringos.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Fichier>
